Alright, so now that we've cleaned this up,
好了，现在我们已经把这里都整理好了
we've got to deploy marks, deploy Funmi.
我们已经有了 "deploy-mocks" 和 "deploy-fund-me"
Let's go ahead and start writing some tests.
让我们开始编写测试吧
And after we write these tests, we're actually going to run that gas estimator
等我们写完这些测试，就要运行 "gas estimator" 了
and using that gas estimator, we're gonna go back, and we're going to update this contract one more time
使用了 "gas estimator" 我们就可以返回去再次更新合约
to make this even cheaper to use and work with.
以使其使用起来更加便宜
And remember, that's going to be one of the advantages of writing these tests
记住，编写这些测试的优势之一
is how we can optimize our contracts to be even faster, more gas efficient, etc,
就是可以通过它们来优化我们的合约，使其更快速，更节省 gas 等等
we want to make sure that we write really good tests,
我们希望确保我们编写的测试非常好
and this is going to be one of our first jumps into these more professional test setups.
这将是我们迈向更专业的测试设置的第一步
So we're going to jump into our test folder,
所以，现在要跳转到我们的 "test" 文件夹
we're going to delete this sample test.js.
我们要删除这个 "sample-test.js"
In our last section, we went over a really minimalistic test, which is great.
在上一节中，我们介绍了一个非常简化的测试，已经很不错了
However, when we get bigger and bigger projects,
然而，当我们的项目越来越大时
we're going to want to start testing more and more different things,
我们就会开始想测试越来越多不同的内容
we're going to get more and more into at least two different types of testing.
我们将至少进行两种不同类型的测试
So if we cd into our test folder,
如果我们进入 ("cd") 到我们的 "test" 文件夹
we're going to make one directory called staging.
我们要创建一个名为 "staging" 的目录
And then we're going to make another directory called unit.
接着我们再创建另一个目录名为 "unit"
And now if we look in our test folder,
现在如果查看我们的 "test" 文件夹
we now have a staging folder, and a unit test folder.
就会有一个 "staging" 文件夹和一个 "unit" 文件夹
Now we're going to talk about two different types of tests.
现在我们要讨论两种不同的测试类型
The first one is going to be something called a unit test.
第一种被称为单元 ("Unit") 测试
Now what is a unit test?
那么什么是 Unit 测试?
Unit testing is a software testing method by which individual units of source code are tested.
Unit 测试是一种软件测试方法，用于测试源代码的各个单元
Basically, what we want to do is in our contracts,
基本上就是，我们要在我们的合约中
we want to test minimal portions of our code to make sure that they work correctly.
测试代码的最小部分，以确保它们正常工作。
Then once our small pieces of the test work,
一旦小的测试片段工作正常
we want to do a staging test or maybe an integration test.
我们就要进行暂存 ("Staging") 测试或者说集成 ("integration") 测试
This might be where we run our code on a test net or some actual network.
这可能就是我们在测试网络或真实网络上运行代码的地方
You can think of a staging test, it's kind of the last stop before you deploy to a main net.
你可以将 Staging 测试看作是部署到主网络前的最后一道检查点
They're not always 100% necessary,
它们并不总是百分百必要的
but they can be really, really helpful.
但它们真的非常非常有用
Remember, we do want to be conscientious of how much we use our test nets,
记住，我们必须要注意我们使用测试网络的频次
but we absolutely would 100% want to make sure that everything works locally
我们必须要确保所有东西都能在本地正常工作
and that we unit test and we run all of our code locally.
而且我们要在本地进行 Unit 测试并运行所有代码
Then we can use staging tests on an actual test net
接着我们才可以在实际的测试网上使用 Staging 测试
to make sure that our code will work with actual other contracts.
以确保我们的代码能与其它合约共同工作
Now unit tests can be done with local Hard Hat Network or a forked Hard Hat Network,
Unit 测试可以使用 "local hardhat" 或者 "forked hardhat"
we'll talk about this for tar Hat Network very soon,
我们很快就会讨论这个 "forked hardhat"
right, now, let's build these unit tests,
但现在，让我们先来构建 Unit 测试
these unit tests are going to be basically what we saw in our last section.
这些 Unit 测试基本上就是我们在上一节中看到的内容
So let's go in and let's jump in and write some of these unit tests.
让我们开始编写这些 Unit 测试吧
So let's create a new test,
我们来创建一个新的测试
we'll call it on me dot test dot j, s.
命名为 "FundMe.test.js"
And we'll start making our tests in here.
我们就从这里开始开展我们的测试
Now, we did test previously in our last section,
我们在上一节中也做了测试，
but our tests here are going to look a little bit differently,
但现在的这个会有一些不同
we're actually going to use hardhat deploy, to automatically set up our tests
我们要用 "hardhat deploy" 来自动设置我们的测试
as if both of these deployed functions had been run.
就像这两个已经运行过的 "deploy" 函数一样
So let's go ahead and get this started.
让我们现在开始吧
So we're still going to do that same setup that we're gonna do describe, we're gonna say fund me.
我们仍然是做相同的设置 `describe("FundMe")`
And this is going to have that async function like so.
这里面是一个 `async function` 就像这样
And in here, we're going to have a before each,
在它的内部，有一个 `beforeEach`
and we're going to have some hits and some describes and everything.
我们还会有一些 `it` 和一些 `describe` 以及一些其它东西
Now since we want to unit test this,
由于我们要进行的是 Unit 测试
we're gonna go a little bit heavier on the test here, and then with our last project,
所以相比上一个项目，我们在这里会进行更加重度的测试
but in the future, we'll go a little bit lighter with some of the tests.
但未来，我们会对一些测试做轻量化处理
So let's get started.
让我们开始吧
If we run yarn Hardhead test right now, we're gonna get zero passing.
如果我们现在运行 `yarn hardhat test` 得到的会是零通过
Now, if we run yarn hardhat coverage,
而如果我们运行的是 `yarn hardhat coverage`
we're gonna get something that looks like this, saying, Hey, you're missing a lot of stuff.
就会得到一些这样的东西，呃，你漏掉了很多东西
So let's try to cover some more lines with our tests.
所以，让我们尝试将测试覆盖更多的行
And one way we can do that is actually we can group our tests based off of different functions.
其中一种方式是，我们可以基于功能的不同来对测试进行分组
So let's have our first set of tests be around our constructor.
我们的第一组测试将围绕着我们的构造函数展开
To do that inside of our first describe, we can add another describe,
因此，在我们的第一个 `describe` 内部，我们可以添加另一个 `describe`
have this describe the just the constructor,
这个 `describe` 只涉及构造函数 ("constructor")
this larger scope will be for the entire Funmi contract.
这个较大的范围适用于整个 "FundMe" 合约
And everything inside this one will just be for the constructor.
而这一个(`describe`)里面的内容只涉及构造函数
So this will also be an async function.
这里也是一个 `async function`
And these tasks will be just for the constructor.
这些任务将只适用于构造函数
But before we even work on this describe, we probably want to deploy our Funmi contract.
但在处理这个 `describe` 之前，得先部署我们的 "FundMe" 合约
So let's learn how to do that.
所以让我们来学习一下如何操作
So we'll do a before each, which will be an async function.
输入 `beforeEach(async function)`
And we're going to deploy our Funmi contract using hard hat deploy.
我们要做的就是部署我们的 "FundMe" 合约，使用 "Hardhat-deploy"
Since we use hard hat deploy,
由于我们使用了 "Hardhat-deploy"
our Funmi contract will come even with our mocks and everything.
所以我们的 "FundMe" 合约会包括我们的 "mocks" 和其它一切内容
So above the before each, let's do let me HDMI.
所以在这个 `beforeEach` 上面，我们要写下 "let fundMe"
And then here, we're going to deploy Funmi,
接着在这里，我们就来部署 "FundMe"
where we're going to deploy our Funmi contract is first by pulling in our deployments object from Harnett deploy.
我们首先通过 "Hardhat-deploy" 获取 "deployments" 对象来部署我们的 "FundMe" 合约
So we'll do const deployments equals require hardhat.
所以就是 `const  = require("hardhat")`
And this deployments object has, has a function called fixture
而这个 "deployments" 对象有一个名为 `fixture` 的函数
with fixture does is it allows us to basically run our entire deploy folder
`fixture` 的作用是允许我们运行整个 "deploy" 文件夹
with as many tags as we want.
并且可以使用任意数量的标签("tags")
You'll notice I added this alt tag in both of our scripts.
你可以看到，我在全部两个脚本中都添加了这个 "all" 标签
This means that in this deployment stuff fixtures,
这意味着，在这个 `deployments.fixture()` 中
it's gonna be a wait deployment of fixtures.
抱歉，应该是 `await deployments.fixture()`
If I run away deployments dot fixture,
如果我运行 `await deployments.fixture()`
I'll run through our deploy scripts on our local network and deploy all of the contracts
就会在我们的本地网络中运行部署脚本并部署全部合约
that we can use them in our scripts and in our testing,
这样我们就可以在我们的脚本和测试中使用它们了
and we can deploy everything in that deploy folder with just this one line.
我们可以直接部署 "deploy" 文件夹中的所有内容，只需要这么一行代码
isn't that helpful.
是不是很好用
Now, once all of our contracts have been deployed, we can start getting them
现在，只要我们的所有合约都部署完毕，就可以开始获取它们了
will say fund me equals await ethers, and we'll pull an ether some hard hat as well.
`fundMe = await ethers`，我们得把 "ethers" 也从 "hardhat" 中获取出来
dot and this is where hard hat deploy is helpful. Again,
`.` 这就是 "Hardhat-deploy" 再次发挥作用的地方了
hard to deploy rapt ether is with a function called Get contract,
"Hardhat-deploy" 为 "ethers" 包装了一个名为 `getContract` 的函数
this get contract function is going to get the most recent deployment of whatever contract we tell it.
这个 `getContract` 函数将获取我们告诉它的任意合约的最新部署
So we'll say get contract of fun to me.
所以我们写下 `getContract("FundMe")`
So this will give us the most recent Lee deployed Funmi contract in just this one line.
这就会为我们提供最新部署的 "FundMe" 合约，只需要这么一行
And now Funmi will be equal to this line here.
现在 `fundMe` 就是等于，这么一行
Now we're going to make a bunch of transactions on our Funmi.
现在我们要在 "FundMe" 上进行一系列交易
To test it. Of course, we can also tell ethers which account we want connected to fund me.
为了进行测试，我们可以告诉 "ethers" 我们想把哪个账户连接到 "FundMe"
So I can say const deployer equals goes away get named accounts,
所以可以这么写 `const deployer = await getNameAccounts`
exactly like we did in our deploy scripts.
就和我们在部署脚本中做的完全一样
And then we just need to import it from our tap
接着我们只需要把它从 "hardhat" 中导入进来就行了
in our deploy scripts
在我们的部署脚本中
we imported get named accounts inside of our input parameters for our deploy function.
我们导入了 "getNameAccounts" 作为 "deploy" 函数的输入参数
Remember getting named accounts and deployments was abstracted from
记住，"getNameAccounts" 和 "deployments" 是从
if we look up here,  from the hard hat runtime environment,
看一下这里，是从 "hardhat" 运行环境中提取出来的
and like I said, the hard hat runtime environment is basically the same thing as hard hat.
就像我说的那样，"hardhat" 运行环境基本上就和 "hardhat" 是一回事
So we can just go ahead and import it like this,
所以我们可以直接这样导入它
actually like this.
应该这样写...
Because we actually need to abstract just the deployer from getting named accounts.
因为我们只需要从 "getNameAccounts" 中提取出 "deployer" 就够了
And now what we can do is we can connect our Deployer to our Fund Me account.
现在我们就可以把 "deployer" 连接到我们的 "FundMe" 上了
So whenever we call a function with fund me,
每当我们用 "fundMe" 调用函数时
it'll automatically be from that the player account, which is great.
它都将自动连接到 "deployer" 账户，这非常好
Another way you can get different accounts
另一种获取不同账户的方式是
directly from your heart had config.
是直接从 "hardhat.config" 中获取
Is you could take const accounts equals await ethers dot get signers,
你可以这样做 `const accounts = await ethers.getSigners`
ethers dot get signers is going to return whatever is in this account section of your network.
`ethers.getSigners` 会返回你 `networks` 中的 `accounts` 部分
If you're on your default network hard hat,
如果你处于 `defaultNetwork` "hardhat" 上的话
it's going to give you a list of 10 fake accounts that we can work with
它就会返回一个包含 10 个虚拟账户的列表以供你使用
you then of course, can do something like const.
所以当然，你就可以进行一些这样的操作
Account one equals accounts.
`accountOne = accounts`
More correctly would be account zero equals account zero and work like that.
更正确的写法可能应该是 `accountZero = accounts[0]` 就像这样
We'll leave that comment that out, just in case you need a reference to it in the future.
我们会把这一段注释掉，以防将来需要参考
Okay, great. So now we have our Funmi contract.
OK 很好，现在我们拥有了 `fundMe` 合约
Let's go ahead and write some tests for testing the constructor.
让我们继续编写测试构造函数的测试
And we're probably going to want to use this deployer object down here.
我们可能需要在下面用到这个 `deployer` 对象
So we'll do let deployer above.
所以我们在上面定义一个 `let deployer`
And we'll do something a little finicky here.
现在我们要处理一些棘手的事情
But we'll say deployer equals Wait, get named accounts, dot Deployer.
我们要改成 `deployer = (await getNameAccounts()).deployer`
And we'll just wrap this up
我们要把它用括号包起来
so that we can just grab this deployer object and assign it to declare like so.
以便我们可以直接获取这个 `deployer` 对象并将其分配给这个 `deployer`
Now in here, we'll create our first test,
现在我们就要创建我们的第一个测试了
we'll say it will say it sets the Agra Gator addresses correctly. Comma will have this be an async function.
写下 `it("sets the aggregator addresses correctly", async function (){})`
And we'll say const response equals await fund me dot,
然后是 `const response = await fundMe.`
let's get this price feed here, fund me dot price feed.
我们来获取一下这里的这个 `priceFeed`，`fundMe.priceFeed()`
And then we'll want to make sure this price feed is going to be the same as our Mk V three aggregator
接着我们要确保这个 `priceFeed` 就是我们的 "MockV3Aggregator"
since we're going to be running these tests locally.
因为我们要在本地运行这些测试
So we should get our mark three V three aggregator up top.
所以我们应该在顶部获取 "mockV3Aggregator"
Let's do let mock v3 aggregate store.
写下 `let mockV3Aggregator`
And we'll grab this address the same way
并以相同的方式获取地址
mockbee Three aggregator equals await ethers dot get contract mockbee Three aggregator comma,
`mockV3Aggregator = await ethers.getContract("MockV3Aggregator", )`
we'll connect this one to the deployer as well.
并同样连接上 `deployer`
So we'll want to say cert dot equals cert dot equal response comma lock v3 aggregator dot address.
所以我们要写的就是 `assert.equal(response, mockV3Aggregator.address)`
And of course we'll want to say const. Assert equals require gy.
当然了，还有 `const  = require("chai")`
Import that from DJI.
从 "chai" 中把它导入进来
Okay, cool.
OK，酷~
Now, let's go ahead and try this out. Yarn hardhat. Test.
现在让我们来试一下 `yarn hardhat test`
Oops, I spelled response wrong. Let's try that again.
哎呀，我拼错了 `response`，来再试一次
Awesome. So this means that we are indeed assigning the price feed address correctly to the Mach v3 aggregator.
太棒了，这就意味着我们确实正确地把 `priceFeed` 分配到 `mockV3Aggregator` 了
Okay, great. Awesome.
OK，非常好，太棒了
I think for now, that's all we really want to do for our constructor.
我想目前这些就是对构造函数所要做的所有事了
Now these two are kind of a nice to have,
这两个东西也很不错
I showed them more just to kind of demo what they look like,
但我展示它们只是为了演示它们是什么
we're going to skip writing tests for them for now.
所以我们暂时不需要为它们编写测试
And we're actually going to go ahead and delete them directly from the contract.
我们直接把它们从合约中删掉
If you want to go ahead and write some tests for them
如果你打算为它们编写测试
and leave them in your examples for your learnings.
并把它们留在你的示例中以供学习的话
You absolutely can pause the video and write some tests for it if you choose so,
你也可以暂停视频，编写测试
but we're going to skip them.
但我会跳过它们
Next though, we are going to move on to fund and running some tests for fun here.
接下来我们将移步到 `fund` 并为其运行测试
So let's go ahead and write describe fund. This will be an async function.
所以我们来写下 `describe("fund", async function() {})`
And in here, we're going to do a number of tests.
这里，我们将进行数个测试
So if we're going to go line by line here,
如果我们要逐行测试这里
what's the first thing that we should look at?
首先应该注意什么？
Well, we should look at this require line we should write a test to see if this contract
actually does fail? If not enough, eath is sent. So let's
go ahead and we'll say it fails, if you don't send enough eath
have this be an async function? Now, how do we test to see if
something fails? Right now we've done assert equals, but if
something fails, we might run into an issue. So for example,
if I run await fund me dot fund, but I don't pass any value to
this transaction. Let's see what happens. I run yarn Hardhead
test. Well, our test is actually going to break VM exception.
While processing transaction reverted with reason string, you
need to spend more eath. So our tests are going to break which
is good. We want this to break. But we want to tell our test
that this is okay. Right? Want to tell that this is okay. So
the way we can do this, and this is where our waffle testing
comes into play. With waffle and with testing, what we can
actually do is we can use the expect keyword and expect
transactions to be reverted and for transactions to fail. So
instead of using assert here, we're actually going to run a
wait expect fund me dot fun 2.2 dot B, that reverted and we've
actually even be more specific here by saying to be reverted
with and then the exact reverted error, you need to spend more
eath. Now if we run our tests, oops expect is not defined. So
we need to import that from Chai. Which chai is being
overwritten by waffle, we see that it does indeed Pass, which
is perfect. So now we have a way to both assert things and expect
things to fail. Awesome, even with the specific failure codes.
Perfect. Let's write some more tests here. Well, we probably
want it to correctly update this data structure. So we could say,
it updates the amount funded data structure, it's going to be
an async function. In here, we're going to need to call fund
v dot fund. However, we're going to need to actually pass some
value with this transaction. And for now, we'll just hard code
the value that we're going to send, say const. Send value is
going to be 112345 678-910-1234 5678, which
is going to be one eath. Another way we can write this though, is
we can use the ethers utility to make this a little bit easier to
read. Because all those zeros are kind of confusing, and it's
hard to tell at first glance what this actually is. So we're
gonna actually use ethers dot utils dot parse ether, one, this
parse ethers utility converts this one into that one with 18
zeros, which makes life a lot easier. If you go to the ethers
documentation, there's also a parts units function where you
can actually convert any unit, either ethers or Gwei. Or really
whatever you want to do, you could convert any number to any
other Aetherium you type. So this is the set value that we're
going to use for our fund. And, and this is definitely going to
be more than our minimum USD of 50. So after we call this fun
function, we'll say const response is going to be equal to
a weight, fund me dot address to Mt funded address to Mt funded
for the deployer dot address. Because remember, this is a
mapping of each address and how much they've actually funded. So
if we use the deployer address, it should give us the amount
that we actually sent. So now we can run assert dot equal
response.to string, right, because this response is going
to be the big number version of how much has been funded by that
account. And that should be the same as our send value.to
string. Since send value, our one should be the exact same as
the amount that we funded, we can run just this one test, or
running yarn, art hat, test, dash dash grep. And we'll put
this in quotes allow funded for this amount funded line. And it
looks like we ran into an issue here, because we don't need to
do deployed at address, we can just do deploy here. And great,
it looks like we are indeed passing. Now if we even run yarn
Hardhead coverage will now see we've got at least a little bit
more coverage here. It's still not going to be great. But we
have much better coverage. We have some statements, some
branches, and at least some functions covered. So this is
awesome. Let's keep going. Are we all done testing our fun
function? Well, probably not. What else can we do with our fun
function? Well, we're also adding funders to a funders
array. So let's go ahead and test for that. So it adds funder
to array of funders has been an async function. And we'll say
await fund mean that fund value is going to be send value. We'll
say const response equals await fund me dot calling the funders
array at index zero. So this will be funder equals await fund
me dot funders zero. And then we'll say assert dot equal
funder should be the same as the Deployer. So let's go ahead and
run this test. We'll hit up a couple times. And we'll change
the GREP to under to array so that it looks for this line. And
perfect. It looks like that one is also passing. Great. So the
money's coming through, the minimum amount is coming through
and our data structures are being updated. Awesome. Now we
could be a little bit more verbose and do even more testing
with this fun function. But I think for the most part, we've
got the gist, right. So now let's go ahead and move on to
the withdrawal function. So we're going to create a new
describe or withdraw. This is going to be an async function.
And let's see what the withdrawal function does. Only
the owner of the contract is going to be able to get the
balance, get the money back. And we're also going to reset all of
the amounts that each one of these users is done. So let's go
ahead and do some withdrawing. Now in order for us to test
withdraw, we probably first want the contract to actually have
some money and so what we can do actually is we can add another
before each in the describe to automatically fund the contract
before we run any tests. So we can say before each async
function. We can say await, fund me dot fund. Value, send value.
Now for all of our tests in this withdrawal scope, we're first
going to fund it with eath. Let's say it can withdraw,
withdraw eath. From a single founder, this would be an async
function. And this is going to be a little bit longer test. So
I'm going to set it up to be an arrange, act and assert test. So
arrange act assert is just sort of a way to think about writing
tests, you want to arrange the test, then you want to act. And
then you want to run the asserts, and you'll see what I
mean in just a second. So we're going to arrange this test,
we're going to set this test up, we want to actually check that
we're correctly withdrawing the ether from a single founder. So
first, we're going to get the starting balance of the
fundraising contract and the starting balance of the
Deployer. So we'll say const. Starting under me, balance,
equals await, fund me dot provider, dot get balance, fund
me dot address. So we're gonna start with the balance of the
fund V contract after it's been funded with some eath. And we're
also gonna get costs start starting, deploy your balance
goes await, fund me dot provider, dot get balance of
deployed employer.
So we're getting the starting balance of the Funmi, we're
getting to the starting balance of the employer so that we can
test later on how much these numbers have changed based off
of what happens when we call the withdrawal function. Now that
we've done a little bit of setup, we can actually run this
withdrawal function, we can do the act here. So we're gonna say
const, trans action response equals await, fund me dot
withdraw. And then we can say const, transaction receipt
equals await transaction response. That Wait, one, and
now we should be able to check to see that the entire fund
rebalance has been added to the deployer balance. So now we can
say const ending fund me balance equals a weight on me that
provider dot get balance of Unreal dot address. Then we can
say const ending deployer balance equals await, fund me
dot provider dot get balance
of Deployer. And now we can just check to see if the numbers work
out here.
So we can say assert dot equal ending fund me balance is going
to be zero, right, because we just withdrew all of the money.
So ending funding balance should be zero. And we'll say assert
dot equal starting fund me balance plus starting deployer
balance. So the starting funds the balance plus the starting
employer balance should equal the ending employer balance.
Since we're grabbing whatever the starting deployer balance
started with plus the starting fund to be balanced, because we
just withdrew all of the starting fund, we balance that
should equal the ending deployer bots. Now a couple of notes
here, since starting Funmi balance is calling from the
blockchain, it's going to be of type a big number, we want to
use big number dot add actually, instead of the plus sign here,
just because it'll it'll make working with our big numbers a
little bit easier. So instead of starting Funmi balance, plus
we're gonna be starting from the balance dot add. Like that. And
that should be good. One other thing about this, though, is
that when we called withdraw our Deployer did what our Deployer
spent a little bit of gas. So this actually isn't accurate. We
actually also need to calculate in the gas cost, so we wouldn't
need to do dot add gas cost. We'd also have to do.to string
because big numbers are objects and so identities a little bit
weird. So to test to see if they're equal, we'll just make
them both strings.